<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A special warrant given forth from the spirit of God (who is Lord over all lords and King over all kings) against the spirit of envy and persecution ... also some descriptions set down how this insufferable enemy (the spirit of persecution) may be known ... / written by Joseph Fuce.</title>
            <author>Fuce, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31719</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12247591</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12247591</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57002</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40524)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57002)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1504:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A special warrant given forth from the spirit of God (who is Lord over all lords and King over all kings) against the spirit of envy and persecution ... also some descriptions set down how this insufferable enemy (the spirit of persecution) may be known ... / written by Joseph Fuce.</title>
                  <author>Fuce, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages faded, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Inner Light.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57002:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57002:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Special VVarrant Given forth (from the SPIRIT of GOD (Who is Lord over all Lords, and King above all Kings) againſt the Spirit of Envy and Perſecution, who hath been, is, and will be the Greateſt Enemy to God and Godlineſs, and to all People.</p>
            <p>ALSO, Some Deſcriptions ſet down how this unſufferable Enemy (the Spirit of Perſecution) may be known, and what he is, and from whence he came, and where he lodgeth in the Night, and what Weapons people may be armed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him when they go to take him, that he may not hurt them, that ſo they may bring him to Judgment, and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence may be paſt upon him.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Sathan ſhall go forth to deceive the Nations, and Gog and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog ſhall appeare together, for the ſtirring up of an Army to Battel againſt the Saints, the Number of whom is as the Sand of the Sea; and they went upon the breadth of the Earth, and compaſſed the Camp of the Saints about, and the Beloved City, and fire came down from God out of Heaven and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured them,</hi> as in <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 20.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Theſe ſhall make war with the Lamb, and the Lamb ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome them, for he is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, </hi>
               <bibl> Rev. 17. 14.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Written by <hi>Joſeph Fuce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1663,</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:57002:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57002:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Special VVarrant Given forth from the Spirit of God.</head>
            <p>A Special Warrant given forth from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God (who is Lord over all Lords, and King above all Kings) againſt the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Envy and Perſecution, which hath, is, and will be the Greateſt Enemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and Godlineſſe, to Kings and Kingdomes, Nobles and Nobility, Neighbours and Neighbourhood; and therefore would the God of the Spirits of all fleſh have both Kings and Nobles, and all other People, in all parts of his Creation, and that more eſpecially in thoſe Parts where Kings, and Nobles, and People of all ſorts profeſſe to owne God, and his Chriſt, to be awakened, and moved to ſtirre and ſtand up, and to ſet unto their helping hand, and to lend their beſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance for the ſtopping, apprehending, and taking this Great and Notorious Enemy to God and all Mankind, from the very Higheſt to the Loweſt of all in the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and to True Religion it ſelfe: With ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions what this Inſufferable Enemy is, and from whence he came, and where he Lodgeth in the Night, and how he may be knowne and taken, and what Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all ſorts are to be Armed with againſt this Thief that cometh in the Night, ſo that they may not be hurt by him, nor hurt one another about taking him,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57002:3"/> and bringing him to Judgement and Condemnation; for they that profeſt themſelves to be Religious people that have gone forth heretoſore, and have not beene Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the True Armour, nor led by the True Leader, they have Struck at this Enemy and miſſed him, and Wounded and Killed one another, and Taken and Impriſoned one another, and let him goe at Liberty in every Nation and Country, City and Towne like a roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lyon to devoure, to the great Griefe of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, who created: Mankind, and <hi>would have them all to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the Truth,</hi> as the Scripture ſaith; and then how peaceable people of all ſorts may live, and how in Life and Spirit they may Serve and Worſhip their Creator, and in Love ſerve and doe one for another as Brethren and Friends and Neighbours, and ſo every one may come to ſit downe under his owne Vine, and none ſhall make him afraid.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What this Great Enemy unto God and Godlineſſe, and all Mankind is, againſt whom this Special Warrant from the Spirit of God goes ſorth?</p>
            <p>This Great Enemy to all Mankind is that Old Envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Spirit of Perſecution that got into <hi>Cain,</hi> and mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſtirred him up againſt his Righteous Brother <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, (Gen. 4, 5, 8.)</hi> So he made <hi>Cain</hi> his Servant to Murther or Kill his Righteous Brother <hi>Abel,</hi> and brought miſery and ſorrow and Everlaſting Torment upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who then became a Vagabond from God to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with a Burthen too heavy for him to beare; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he built a City to make himſelfe an Habitation, yet his Puniſhment: was Greater than he could beare, becauſe he had done the Murthering Spirits Worke (in Slaying his Brother) and ſo became worthy of Everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Puniſhment, like unto him that was a Murtherer from the Beginning: And the ſame Envious, Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Murthering Spirit was in <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who burdened and grievouſly Oppreſſed and Afflicted the Lords Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57002:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> for a long time, <hi>(Exod. 3. 7.)</hi> which grieved the Lords Spirit, who heard the Groanings of his People in <hi>Egypt, (Exod. 5,</hi> to the 14.) And this Envious Spirit made <hi>Pharaoh</hi> the King do ſo Wickedly againſt the minde of God as to provoke the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to bring the Plagues on the Kings owne ſelfe, and the whole Land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and yet this Great Enemy to the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome would not let the King be quiet, but made him to oppreſſe them more than before, and at laſt to purſue the Lords People with a Great Army of Horſe-men and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, intending to Deſtroy thoſe whom the Lord had Choſen to himſelfe to be his People; and by ſo doing the King brought everlaſting deſtruction upon himſelfe and all his Hoſt, who were deſtroyed by water in the Red Sea; and that was the worke of the Envious Spirit to bring to everlaſting deſtruction. And the ſame Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my was in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> and <hi>Belſhazar,</hi> and in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents and Princes, and in <hi>Haman,</hi> and in all the reſt of the envious Enemies of God and his People in thoſe Generations. <hi>(Eſther 7.)</hi> And oh how did that great Enemy, the Spirit of Perſecution, betray <hi>Haman</hi> even to the Gallows to be Hanged for deviſing miſchief againſt poore <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and all the Jewes, which were the Lords People? And alſo how was the great King <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> deceived by the ſame Deceitful Spirit of Envy and Perſecution, that ſtirred him up to Perſecute the Lords Holy Children, and to exalt himſelfe in the Pride of his heart, until his Kingdome was taken, and he drove our from amongſt men to eat Graſſe like an Oxe, and his Body to be wet with the Dew, until his Haires were growne like Eagles Feathers, and his Nailes like Birdes Clawes, <hi>(Dan. 4. 33.)</hi> And he humbled himſelfe, and looked up to Heaven, and his Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing returned to him, <hi>(Dan. 5.)</hi> by which he ſpake, to the great Praiſe of God and his Kingdome, and Wayes, and Judgements; and he confeſt, that they that walk in Pride, he is able to abaſe, and he knew it was the Moſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57002:4"/> High that Ruled in the Kingdome of Men, and that he appointeth over it whoſoever he will.</p>
            <p>And then after <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, Belſhazar</hi> was King, and Reigned, <hi>(Dan. 5.)</hi> and he made a great Feaſt to a thouſand of his Lords, and drunk Wine before them, and then he ſent for the Veſſels, that his Father had taken out of the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and he, and his Wives, and Nobles drank wine in them; and in the ſame Houre came forth Fingers of a Mans Hand, and wrote upon the Wall of the Kings Palace (for a ſigne againſt the King,), and the King ſaw the part of the Hand that Wrote, and his Countenance was then chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and his Thoughts troubled him, ſo that he cryed to bring in the Aſtrologers, the Chaldeans, and the Southſayers, which were the Wiſe Men of <hi>Babylon,</hi> to ſee if they could read the Writing, and tell the King the Interpretation thereof, which none of them could doe; then the King and his Nobles were ſore troubled and aſtoniſhed: and in that time of trouble the Queen remembred <hi>Daniel</hi> the Lords Servant, in whom was ſound the Spirit of Light and Wiſdome, who read the Writing, and told the King the Interpretation, which was, that God had numbred thy Kingdome, and finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, and he told him, <hi>Thou art Weighed in the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and art found wanting, and thy Kingdome is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and given to the Medes and Perſians.</hi> And the King advanced and honoured <hi>Daniel</hi> to be the Ruler in the Kingdome, although that Night <hi>Belſhazar</hi> was ſlain, and his Kingdome tooke from him by <hi>Darius;</hi> and then it pleaſed <hi>Darius</hi> to ſet over the Kingdome an Hundred and Twenty Princes, <hi>(Dan. 6.</hi> to the end,) that ſhould be over the whole Kingdome, and over three Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, of whom this <hi>Daniel</hi> was firſt, and he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the other, and they were to give accounts unto him, and then the King ſhould have no Damage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was an excellent Spirit in <hi>Daniel;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King thought to ſet him over the whole Realme,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57002:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſo both the King and Princes, and all, were like to doe well, and be in peace, becauſe of that excellent Spirit in <hi>Daniel,</hi> who would let the King have no Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; for the Damage, diſhonour, confuſion; overthrow, and utter deſtruction came upon the Kings and their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, by reaſon of their following the Proud, Envious, Darkning Spirit of Errour, that was known by his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and Enmity; but when the Excellent Spirit of Light and Wiſdome, that was found in <hi>Daniel</hi> the Lords ſervant, was hearkned unto, then the King was lyable to have no Damage, although <hi>Daniels</hi> way of Worſhipping of God was altogether contrary both to King and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet all was well towards the King and Kingdome and Princes and Preſidents, becauſe of that Excellent Spirits leading <hi>Daniel.</hi> But then the Old Serpent, which is the Devil, the King of Pride, and the greateſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayer of mans Soul and Body, which is and ever was the chiefe in doing miſchiefe, the Perſecutor and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer of Gods People, I ſay, this ſubtle Serpent ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spirit of God and of Wiſdome (that was found in <hi>Daniel)</hi> bearing Rule ſo in the King, and over the Princes, that there was like to be no Damage to the King, nor <hi>Daniel,</hi> nor Princes, nor Preſidents, ſo that all was well and in Peace, and his Kingdome of Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Pride and Darkneſſe lay waſt, then marke, how ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly he gets in amongſt the Princes, and begets them into Pride and Diſcontent, becauſe of <hi>Daniel's</hi> being ſet above them, for that Excellent Spirits ſake that no evil might beſall the King or Kingdome; and when this proud Envious Spirit was got up, in and among the Princes and Preſidents, he exalted them into Pride and Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedneſſe with their places, and then they began to watch for evill againſt honeſt harmleſſe <hi>Daniel</hi> the Lords Servant, and knowing they could find nothing againſt him, except it were concerning the Worſhip and Service of his God, which was differing from all their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Services; yet all was well, and no Damage
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57002:5"/> was againſt the King or Princes by Faithful-<hi>Daniels</hi> Worſhipping and Serving his God, though differing from them all, becauſe of that Excellent Spirit of Light and Wiſdome that was found in <hi>Daniel:</hi> And then this Serpent led the Preſidents and Princes ſubtilly to goe to the King, and to ſtir up the King to make a Law and Decree for Conformity, to make all Bow and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to their way of Worſhip, or to be caſt into the Lyons Den, intending this miſchiefe againſt poore <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> becauſe he was confirmed and ſtedfaſt in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service of his God, and alſo Faithful to man in what he could doe for Conſcience ſake, or in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he undertooke whomſoever bare Rule, becauſe there was in him an Excellent Spirit; and the King <hi>Darius</hi> being innocent of their intent, and not foreſeeing their Plot they laid againſt <hi>Daniel,</hi> in ſtirring him up and preſſing him to make a Law, or Seale a Decree about Service and Worſhip, that none might ask a Petition of any, God or Man, for thirty Dayes, ſave thee O King, ſo for all to Conſorme at ſuch a time, or to be caſt into the Lyons Den: And this Wicked Cunning Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent he ſtirred up the Princes, and Preſidents, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Kingdome, to Aſſemble together and vehemently to urge the King to Signe their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Decree, that it might be unalterable; and when he had perſwaded the King, and he had Sealed the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute or Decree, then they Aſſembled themſelves and tooke <hi>Daniel</hi> Praying before his God, as he did afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, then they came neere and ſpake before the King of his Decree, and of <hi>Daniel,</hi> who could not for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake leave the Worſhip and Service of his God, although the Decree was Sealed againſt him; but when the King did ſee, how it reflected upon his True and Faithfull Subject <hi>Daniel,</hi> he was ſore diſpleaſed with himſelfe, and ſet his heart on <hi>Daniel</hi> to Deliver him, and he laboured till the going downe of the Sun to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him; and then thoſe men preſſed upon the King
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57002:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> to have the Decree executed upon <hi>Daniel,</hi> who was brought according to the Decree, that was contrived in the Envy of their hearts, and caſt into the Den of Lyons, and the King Believed, and ſaid to <hi>Daniel, Thy God whom thou ſerveſt continually, will Deliver thee;</hi> then the King went to his Palace, and paſſed the Night paſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, neither were Inſtruments of Muſick brought before him, and his Sleep went from him: But oh how glad was he in the Morning, when he ſaw how that <hi>Daniel</hi> was ſaved by his God, and that becauſe of his Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Innocency that was found before the Lord, and who had wronged no man; and then the King in the exceeding Joy and Gladneſſe of his Heart, cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Daniel</hi> to be taken up out of the Den; when they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken him up, no manner of hurt was ſound about him, becauſe he believed in his God; and the King commanded, and they brought thoſe men which had accuſed <hi>Daniel,</hi> and they caſt them, and their wives and children into the Lyons Den, and they were deſtroyed; And thus were they blinded by the ſpirit of darkneſs and envy, and betrayed even unto death, and that was the fruit and work of the envious ſpirit of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to ſtir up to deſtroy the moſt honeſt and upright in the ſight of God and man, from off the earth, or elſe, to ſtir up, and lead ſuch deſtroyers to be deſtroyed, and that more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, about and concerning Religion and Worſhip; and if I were led to ſpeak of what I ſee of this ſoul-betraying ſpirit of envy and perſecution, and of his fruit, ſurely it would ſill a larg volume, but the Spirit of the Lord (who hath made men wiſe in this Generation) leads me briefly to hint of ſome of the fruits of the old ſpirit of perſecution, in this ſpecial War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to all ſorts of people in Chriſtendom, ſo called, who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſideration with the Light of Chriſt in their Conſciences, may ſee thoſe things to be true, &amp; that ſo much the more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe the Lord in the largneſs of his love hath ſpoken ſo plainly, and called unto man ſo often in this age by his Spirit, through many of his choſen veſſels, who have ſuffered deeply by all the Powers that have born rule, ever ſince we depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from evil, and by the voyce of the ſpirit (through the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57002:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> Lords choſen veſſels) have many minds been turned from darkneſs to light in their own Conſciences, which hath made this Generation wiſer than many Generations heretofore in the Apoſtacy; beſides the great and marvelous works that God hath brought to paſs in the ſight of this Generation of men, in overturning, and changing, and converting thouſands from darkneſs to light, and from evil to good, and from envy to true love; beſides the overturning of Governours and Governments and Armies, and that at the laſt, without fighting or ſhedding of blood, which is enough to awaken this Generation, into a conſideration of things paſt, preſent, and to come. And thus did the old Serpent work before the days of Chriſt's coming in the fleſh, to end the Jews worſhip in out-ſide things, and their Law, and to ſet up the everlaſting worſhip of God in the Spirit.</p>
            <p>And now take notice, how the old Dragon got in among the Jews, who had <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets writings, who had been great ſufferers, and who had known by writings how their fore-fathers were ſcattered, and led into <hi>Babilon,</hi> after God by a mighty hand had brought them through the Red Sea and Wilderneſs; and theſe profeſſing Jews ſaid, if they had been in the days of their fathers, they would not have perſecuted the Prophets; but while they were in their Zeal, worſhipping in outward things, the envious ſpirit of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion got into them, and blinded their minds, and hardned their hearts; and in thoſe days, this ſpirit of envy and murther and perſecution, began to work in <hi>Herod</hi> againſt Chriſt, for he ſent forth, and ſlew all the male children in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and in all the coaſts thereof, thinking to deſtroy Chriſt, <hi>(Acts 13.)</hi> And after <hi>John</hi> was beheaded: And ſee what the ſpirit brought <hi>Herod</hi> to at the laſt, he was eaten with Worms: And becauſe the Envious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Jews did not look for the Meſſiah or Chriſt to come in ſo low a degree, as to be born in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and laid in a Manger, they knew him not: And although their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers had ſuffered perſecution and great affliction, and they had ſaid they would not have perſecuted the Prophets, whoſe words they had, which propheſied of Chriſt, who wrought wonders and miracles among them, yet they Crucified the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57002:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> Prince of life; and theſe were they that worſhipped in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Synagogues together with their Prieſts and Rulers, that were ſtirred up by this perſecuting ſpirit, moſtly through the Chief Prieſts, againſt Chriſt and his Diſciples, who went up and down preaching the truth, and doing good, and wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no man; yet they cryed vehemently, <hi>Let him be Crucified:</hi> And as they Crucified Chriſt, ſo they perſecuted his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and put many of them to death, and provoked the Lord againſt them, until he gave them up to be ſcattered, and to be a hiſſing to all the Nations, as the natural ſeed of thoſe Jews are at this day, ſo were they blinded and hardned, and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed to utter ruine, as the perſecutors had been before by the old Serpent, the ſpirit of envy and perſecution; and then when he had done his worſt againſt Chriſt and Chriſtians, in and through the Heathen, Jews, Rulers, Prieſts and people of all ſorts, then he got in amongſt them that were called Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that did not watch in the Light, and low meekneſs of ſpirit, which were ſuch as had the Sheeps cloathing, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly were ravening Wolves, the ravening, wolviſh, doggiſh, envious ſpirit of perſecution made them ſo, and ſuch in that nature had a form of godlineſs, but denyed the power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and from ſuch the true Chriſtians were to turn away, who were in the meek Spirit, and harmleſſe innocent nature of Chriſt, that kept them always ready to do good, and to receive wrong, rather than to do any wrong, to Jew, or Gentile, or the falſe Brethren, that were falſe like the Jews; and then this envious perſecuting ſpirit led the deceivers that came to the Saints in Sheeps cloathing, but inwardly were ravening Wolvs, out into the world, and they that were of the world went after them into a profeſſion of Chriſt, and yet of the worlds nature, and they got a form of godlineſs, but denyed the power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and from ſuch the Saints were to turn away, and ſo there was a difference in the nature of them that profeſſed Chriſt, for ſome were of the Lambs nature, and others of the worlds nature, yet all profeſſed God and Chriſt, and from that, they had all the names of Chriſtians, but all were not of the divine nature of Chriſt; and this was in the latter days, or laſt times, of the Apoſtles age, as <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>Little Children, it is the laſt</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:57002:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>time, as ye have heard that Anti-chriſt ſhall come, even now there are many Anti-chriſts;</hi> whereby they knew that they were the laſt times, and the Anti-chriſts went out from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles into the world, and the world went after them, and ſo the Apoſtacy came in, and then they dayly encreaſed in the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour &amp; degeneration, from the (leader) pitiful, meek, ſuffering and ſaving ſpirit; ſo darkneſs, ignorance, hardneſs of heart, and envy encreaſed among them that had the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, but had loſt the nature of Chriſt, and the ſpirit of envy and perſecution began to appear to be chief among them; then the Beaſt roſe up out of them, that were like the Sea, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this impoſing power from the old Dragon, that ſtirred up the Jews to Cruciſie the Lord of life; and ſo the Beaſt ſet up an Image, and cauſed the people to worſhip his Image; and the Saints of the moſt High that would not worſhip the Image of the Beaſt, nor receive his Mark in their foreheads, or in their right hands, were to be ſtain, ſuch was their impoſition for their imagined way of worſhip, and they made war with the Saints of the moſt High, and overcame them, and killed both ſmall and great, that would not worſhip the Beaſt and his Image; and the man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> child Chriſt Jeſus was caught up to God, and the woman ſled into the wilderneſs, where ſhe hath been nouriſhed in the time of Apoſtacy, and blindneſs of peoples minds; and oh what havock hath this ſoul-betraying ſpirit of envy and perſecution made, with and among the Chriſtians, ſo called in the Apoſtacy? &amp; how hath he ſet Kings, &amp; Princes, and Nations, and Kingdomes, and Prieſts, and people, one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another about Religion and Worſhip? and how griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly have people been enſlaved through Chriſtendome by this ſpirit of perſecution, to martyr and murther one another, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> againſt the <hi>Proteſtants, Lutherans, Presbyterians,</hi> and other Sects, and the <hi>Lutherans, Proteſtants, Presbyterians,</hi> and others, againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and all about Religion, and all called Chriſtians, and all lyable to ſuffer (as often they have done) by the Heathen; ſo miſchievous and treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous hath this perſecuting ſpirit betrayed people to death, about their form of Worſhip, that hath ſtood in outward things, and all hath been without the ſpirit of love unfeigned,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57002:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> and out of natures affection; and they were the perſecuters that had the powers of the earth on their ſides, and were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt; and ſo they have rowled to and fro, and tumbled up and down like the Sea, and broke one another like the waves thereof, and deſtroyed and devoured one another like the fiſhes of the Sea, and beaſts of the field, and all about Service and Worſhip, and every one counting his own way right, and all others wrong, while all their hands have been full of blood, and all are out of the Spirit that teaches to love enemies, and to forgive enemies, and ſo to overcome the evil with the good ſpirit of love and forgiveneſs; and ſo they have been all wrong in perſecuting one another, and revenging one upon another, and ſeeking to overcome one another with the evil ſpirit of cruelty and perſecuting, and ſo the very name <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> is abhorred among the Heathen, <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Indians,</hi> and <hi>Jewes</hi> alſo, by reaſon of this deviliſh ſpirit of envy and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, which hath made ſlaves of whole Nations of people called Chriſtians, who hath done or fulfilled the luſts of the Old Dragon, from whence all theſe Wars and Jars, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling one another about Religion and Service, did firſt ariſe in this long Night of Apoſtacy, which Chriſt, the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſaid ſhould come, wherein no man ſhould work, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now take notice how this great enemy hath wrought in this Age in which we live, after that it pleaſed God to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten mens underſtandings ſomwhat more than in ſome A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges paſt, and to awaken the Conſciences of ſome to ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God more ſtrictly than before: Then they began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form from ſome Idolatry, as they counted it, and to learn ſome of the Traditions of their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, which were almoſt all Papiſts, about a hundred years ago, and many were zealous for godlineſs; but then this ſpirit began to work afreſh among people in this our native Country of <hi>England;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome reformation inwardly, the enemy got up among them, and led many into new inventions, and Traditions of their own; and then the envious ſpirit of perſecution got up, and then they that were in the old Traditions and Invented
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57002:8"/> wayes of Service and Worſhip, and they that imagined and invented new Inventions, and ſet up other Traditions, roſe up one againſt another in the ſpirit of envy and perſecution. And oh what a work hath been within this 20 years, which may never be forgotten. Firſt, what killing and ſlaying one another, and throwing down others Traditions, and ſlighting their Way and Miniſters, and ſetting up others that had ſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len more of the good words and fair Speeches, whereby they ſo much the more deceived the hearts of the ſimple? And oh how lovly were the Reformed Miniſtry and people! and how did they crow over others that did not reform, while they had a dunghil to ſtand upon? and then what hunting was there among the beſt reformed Miniſters for great Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and ſometimes laying two or three little ones together, and then they mounted into the chief Seats in their Temples called Churches, and there they cryed againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and againſt the Common-Prayer, and Organs, and Singing Boyes, and the like, and yet would take Tythes, which was the <hi>Romiſh</hi> wages and hire, although they refuſed to do the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Service; and ſo that hath ſtood, notwithſtanding their changing; and that was not enough to ſerve ſome, but they would run and complain to the Powers that then were to get Augmentations: And notwithſtanding their good words and fair ſpeeches, their hearts went after their covetouſneſs. And as the Prieſts did, ſo did many Rulers: Oh how they ſought after Lordſhips, and others Eſtates, and ſo threw down others, and exalted themſelves, notwithſtanding their Reformation, ſo full of Pride, Covetouſneſs, and Envy, was their hearts: And when the <hi>Preſbiterians, Independents,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> and the like, who pretended for Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, were at the higheſt, and had the Rule among them, and the <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> were very low in <hi>England</hi> (which one would think were enough to make them remember a poor low, and afflicted people, throughout their Generation) I ſay their Liberty of Conſcience was but to themſelves, for it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reached back to the Common-Prayer men, nor the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt:</hi> Then the Lord would try them a little further with a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57002:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> poor, deſpiſed, low and humble people, whom he choſe out from among them all; ſome from the Common-Prayer men, and ſome from the <hi>Presbiterians,</hi> and ſome from the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants,</hi> and ſome from the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> and the like; and when the Lord had called us, and begun to break our hearts in pieces by the power of his living Word, that was as a hammer in us, and thereby were we made to fear, tremble, ſhake and quake, and weep and mourn, like the holy men of God in Ages paſt: And when the Lord was thus fitting us for his own ſervice, to ſound ſorth his praiſes, then the Profeſſors they ſtood and wondred; ſcoffed and mocked at us, calling us <hi>Quakers,</hi> both Rulers, Prieſts, and people; and although they pretended Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> yet we were haled out of our Meetings, and put in the Stocks, and beaten and abuſed, and impriſoned (for declaring the Truth) and our Goods made havock of, becauſe we could not uphold ſuch covetous hypocrites, as theſe Prieſts were: And much more did we ſuffer, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their talk of Liberty of Conſcience; and then in the power of God we were made to cry out againſt deceit and hypocriſie, for which we ſuffered by the hands of the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable; and this wicked, envious, perſecuting ſpirit, was the Author of all that miſchief: And we were ſo mortified in our minds, and humbled in our ſpirits, by the opperation of the power of our God, which we received in his eternal Light, that we could do them no evil, but good for evil; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by were we made both able and willing to do, or to ſuffer, whatſoever we were called unto for his Names ſake; and waiting in his true Light, we have ſeen how this wicked ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betraying ſpirit of envy and perſecution, hath betrayed and took Captive, and then made ſlaves of the ſons and daughters of men, both ſouls and bodies, who were Gods people by Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, but the Devil, he ſtole their hearts and minds from God, and out of the true Liberty of the ſons of men, as men; and in that wretched and deplorable ſtate were all Mankind in, we as well as others, before the new Creation, or being Regenerated, and Ranſomed, and created again in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus unto good works; by his living Word; and then the love of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57002:9"/> God the Father, which he hath ſhed abroad in our hearts, did abound towards all Mankind upon the face of the whole earth, inſomuch that our hearts were made ſad, and heavy, and our ſouls did mourn in ſecret for them, and on their behalf, to ſee their bondage and ſlavery, and how this unreaſonable, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, perſecuting ſpirit, ruled over them, and made them unwilling to hearken unto the counſel of God their Creator, who ſent many of us in his love and pity, to call them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that they might receive the remiſſion of ſins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and embrace the love and mercy that God held forth unto them-wards, not only in theſe neer Nations, out alſo to them that are afar of; but they have required us evilly for our good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, and true love towards them, both ſoul and body, even becauſe we have told them the Truth, and ſpoke againſt, and ſtruck at their greateſt Enemy, the ſoul-betraying ſpirit of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and perſecution; and they would not hear and conſider, nor lay thoſe things to heart, which moſt concerned their peace, and everlaſting welfare of body and ſoul, but went on in hardneſs of heart, very contrary to the Light of Chriſt in their own Conſciences, until they had filled up their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of iniquity, and provoked the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> utterly to overturn them, and caſt them out to be made a prey upon by the old betrayer of Perſecuters to be deſtroyed and cut off as others have been before in Ages paſt, and that is the perſecuting ſpirits work, to lead to deſtroy, and then to bring deſtroyers to deſtruction alſo, as all may ſee, that reads theſe lines with a good underſtanding. And this is a true and brief Deſcription of this greateſt and moſt deſtructive enemy of Mankind in the whole Creation, and how he hath betrayed Kings and Princes, and Kingdoms, and Nations of <hi>Jewes,</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and Chriſtians, ſo called, and alſo how he may be known and apprehended by a ſpecial Warrant.</p>
            <p>And further, be it known unto all that reads and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands, that God, the Creator of Mankind, hath wholly and firmly decreed the taking and binding of this old Serpent, which is the Devil, ſhortly, and to caſt him into the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs pit, and to ſhut and ſeal him down, that he may deceive
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57002:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Nations no more; and God will alſo caſt them into the Lake, to be tormented with the Devil and his Angels for ever, that will not return to the Lord in the time while he calleth unto them, and ſtriveth by his Light and Spirit with them, and waiteth to be good, and merciful, and gracious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; and this old Dragon is in a great rage, becauſe his Kingdome and Reign draws towards an end, and <hi>he hath but a ſhort time,</hi> as it is written in <hi>Rev. 12.</hi> And then ſhall thoſe words of God be fulfilled, which he ſpake by the mouth of his Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, For out of Zion ſhall go forth-the Law, and the word of the Lord from Jeruſalem; and he ſhall judg among the Nations, and rebuke many people; and they ſhall beat their Swords into Plow-ſhares, and their Spears into Pru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing hocks; and Nation ſhall not lift up Sword againſt Nation, neither ſhall they learn war any more, and they ſhall rejoyce together in love, and cry, Come let us walk in the light of the Lord, and go up unto the houſe of God that made us; for he ſhall teach us of his wayes:</hi> And then ſhall the people ſing a new Song unto the Lord, and his people ſhall praiſe him from the ends of the earth, and they that were as a barren Wilderneſs ſhall lift up their voyce unto the moſt High, and ſhout for joy of heart, to ſee the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, that old Serpent, which is the Devil, that betrayed them into the curſe and bitterneſs, and enmity one againſt another, taken and bound, and caſt out into the bottomleſs pit, and ſealed down, that he no more can deceive them; and then all may dwell together in love ſafely, and their ſouls greatly to rejoyce in the Lord of Hoſts, and be exceeding joyful in God their Saviour, who cloaths his with the Robe of righteouſneſs, and covereth them round about with the garment of ſalvation; <hi>And the Wolf and the Lamb ſhall feed together, and the Lyon ſhall eat ſtraw like the Bullock, and they ſhall not hurt, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy in all my holy Mountain, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we the people, whom God hath called, and choſen, and made faithful and acceptable to himſelf, through the work of his Son. Jeſus Chriſt in us, and for us, who are thereby made the firſt fruits unto God, in this Age, after the long Night of Apoſtacy (into the groſſe darkneſs, and great igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) from the true Light and Spirit of God, and Chriſt, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57002:10"/> reveals and gives the knowledge of the things of God; and from the firſt of our true convincement of ſin and evill, by the Light in our Conſciences; and from that very day in which God began to work in this great work of converſion out of the evil envious nature, into true love and humility, and out of the fleſh into the Spirit, and to be of the new Birth, being born of the bleſſed womb of love, and to be tranſlated out of the Kingdome of darkneſs and Satan, into the Kingdome of the Dear Son of God: I ſay, even from the very beginning unto this day, have we been hated, rejected, vilified, deſpiſed and reproached, and greatly afflicted and perſecuted, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed beyond meaſure; and all hath been for the exerciſe of our Conſcience in the Service of God, and in love and good will towards men. And thus have they ſought to weaken and break us, and ſcatter us into diviſion, like themſelves, and ſo to wear us out; and none of all the Powers of the earth that hath reigned in their time, hath been for us, but againſt us: But the Lord God Almighty, who raiſed us up out of the Duſt, he hath been with us, and among us all along, and his right hand hath upheld us, and his outſtretched arm hath ſuſtain'd us, and they of us that had uſed carnal weapons heretofore, ſome in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Kings Army, and ſome in the Parliaments Army, when they came to ſeel the ſtroak of the Sword of the Spirit of God upon that nature that led to draw the Sword; then he fell and periſhed by the Sword of the Spirit, that led to draw the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sword, as Chriſt ſaid it ſhould be; and notwithſtanding the great occaſions, and provocations without number, that hath been given us, we have been kept (by the power of God, and through Faith in Chriſt) from putting forth a hand or a finger, to take up a carnal Sword, or other weapon, for, or againſt any creature any more, notwithſtanding the tumults, changes, overturnings &amp; ſtrivings, &amp; buffettings, that hath been among the ſons of men, ſince the Lord, in the infiniteneſs of his love, hath called us out from amongſt them, into peace with God on earth, and love to all Man-kind, who are his creatures. But many of us have been moved of the Lord to break our Swords in pieces, and other Inſtruments that were prepared againſt creatures, ſo that they might do no hurt; and this was as a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57002:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> teſtimony that we ſhould war no more, as we hope whole Nations will do in due time, when God hath ſlain the enmity that is in and among them by the power of his love, which is ſtronger than Death, as he hath done in us, Glory and Honour be given to our God, who lives for evermore, who hath brought us to ſtand witneſſes for him, and of his works, as a Pattern to all Mankind upon the face of the whole earth; and as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>By this ſhall all men know that you are my Diſciples, if you have love one towards another:</hi> And through Faith and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Long-ſuffering, with love &amp; goodneſs have we been made inſtruments to overcome the hearts and minds of many which hath been turned to the Light in their own Conſciences, and to the Grace of God given unto them; and it is given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, and remaineth in our hearts, to continue in love to our very enemies, in the Faith and Patience, unto the finiſhing our courſe, for the Name and Glory of God, whether it be by life or death; for we have full aſſurance, how that it is better to dye in the Lord, than to live in ſin. But let all ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael</hi> know aſſuredly, that <hi>the rod of the wicked ſhall not alwayes be upon the backs of the the righteous;</hi> for God will remove the yoak from off their necks, and wipe away all tears from their eyes, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away, although ſome may, as ſome hath finiſhed their teſtimony in being ſlain for the Word of God, and are received into the Kingdome of everlaſting peace, and Glory for ever; and our warfare is ſpiritual, and our weapons are not carnal, but mighty, through God, to the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down of ſtrong holds, and to the cutting down of every thing that riſeth up againſt Chriſt within, that all may be inſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection unto him, whoſe right it is to reign; and ſo our victory is ſpiritual, and we do give thanks unto God, who hath given us victory over ſin and death, hell, and the grave, and over the tempting ſpirit of envy &amp; perſecution in our own particulars, through faith in Chriſt Jeſus, who is the great Shepherd and Biſhop of our ſouls; and we do not at all deſire victory over mens perſons, as they do, who ſtrive and fight with carnal wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, but our ſtriving, and ſmiting, and fighting with our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual weapons is againſt ſin, and he that tempts to ſin and, evil, which is the greateſt enemy to mans everlaſting peace, who is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57002:11"/> the Devil and Dragon, and in the power of the meek ſpirit and Lambs nature, our-ſtroke is and ſhall be againſt him, in all his appearances within and without, as it hath been in the pure love of God the Father, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto whom be honour and glory, now and for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now all you that do own this Special Warrant from God, and his Law and Command from him, which is Light in every Conſcience, and that which it requires, and are awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſtirred up thereby, againſt the ſpirit of envy and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, and in whoſe hearts it is to joyn with the Lamb, to make war with the Dragon, lend your ears to wiſdomes voyce in you, and ſo far as theſe lines are according to the ſame, even ſo be inſtructed, how, and with what to arm your ſelves, ſo that you may not be overcome with this perſecuting ſpirit, nor do any hurt to any of the Sons or Daughters of men, for as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Wiſdome is better than ſtrength,</hi> or weapons of war in this work, and the lips of knowledge is a precious Jewel, and every purpoſe (herein) is eſtabliſhed by Counſel; and with good advice make war, for I, ſaith the Lords Spirit, will make the ſoul-betraying ſpirit of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion feel the ſtroak, and woe, and miſery, and plagues, and Vials double filled of the wrath of the Almighty ſhall come upon the head and crown of thee thou ſubtle Serpent; but I have pity and bowels of mercy towards all mankind whom I have Created, ſaith the Lord, and I will wait yet a little longer for the return of the captivated ones, that I may ſhew mercy unto them, that do look unto me from the ends of the earth and be ſaved, and that I may ſhew compaſſion unto ten thouſand times ten thouſands of thoſe that do return at my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, and come unto me by true and unſeigned repentance, yea, a numberleſſe number, that I may be exceeding good, and gracious unto them, as I have been unto thouſands, that are already come home unto me by my true and everlaſting Light, ſaith the Creator of mankind.</p>
            <p>And now all you that do own, and obey Gods Special War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, the Light which he hath ſent forth into your own hearts and conſciences, you are all required to wait low in it, to ſee what you are to be armed with, and then to receive it in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57002:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> Light, and put it on, then you are ſtill to wait, and to keep low, to hear the voyce of the meek ſoul-ſaving Spirit, and then to obey, and meekly to follow him, who is the Captain of our ſalvation, and then you will ſee how you are to war, and fight againſt the foes of your own houſe in every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and that not without hope of overcoming; and ſo, as you put off the works of darkneſſe, put on hope for an Helmet, and faith and love for your breſt-plate and your ſhield, and let righteouſneſſe be your covering, and keep low in the patience, and <hi>let your feet be ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpel of peace; and put on therefore (as the Elect of God) bowels of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, kindneſſe, humbleneſſe of mind, meekneſſe, long-ſuffering, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing one another, &amp; forgiving one another: If any man hath a quarrel againſt any, even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo do ye; and above all theſe things put on Charity, which is the bond of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and ſo take unto you the whole Armour of God, and hold faſt the ſword of the Spirit, which is the power and word of God, that ſo you may be able to quenoh the fiery darts of the enemy;</hi> and through the ſtrength of your Armour, and ſharpneſſe of your weapons, and through the word of God, and his grace, and the word of patience, or the opperation of his power to effect the work in you, you may be made victorious in the end of the Lambs war with the Dragon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in your particulars, that you may enjoy the preſence and peace of God to your own ſouls, and then will you be for peace among men; and verily, this, thouſands of your own ſelves cannot be ignorant of, how that there hath been many thouſands, that have gone forth againſt the old Serpent in ſeveral Sects ſince the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dayes in the Apoſtacy, and for want of the inward ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Armour, and weapons, and love, and wiſdome to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, and to beat the enemy out of their own hearts firſt, they have armed themſelves with outward Armour, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal weapons, and ſo in the ignorance have roſe up one againſt another, and ſmote and killed one another about Religion and Worſhip, and what grievous havock hath been made about ſervice of God in killing one another, and ſo the Devil hath eſcaped, and creatures hath ſuffered, and this hath been in the night, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Even as a great mans ſervants, although their Lord
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57002:12"/> and maſter was very patient and exceeding loving, and kind to them all, and though they all did amiſs, and contrary to his will, yet he continued his goodneſs to them all, to ſee if they would learne to doe as he would have them, and be quiet one with another, and if they would not, but continue in naughtineſſe, and rebellion againſt him, and one againſt another, then at the laſt he would reward them according to their doings; but thoſe ſervants after they had done evil againſt their Lord and maſter, they would not agree together, but find fault one of anothers ſervice, and then fight and beat one another impatiently about their maſters ſervice, and ſo provoke one another the more, till the enmity become ſo great that they began to kill one another, and then blood that toucheth blood, and ſo ſome deſtroyed others; and when he that was Lord over all ſaw that, he called them to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that had killed their fellow ſervants, and required their blood at their hands; ſo they that had killed without mercy, they muſt dye without mercy; and that hath been, and will be the end that the perſecuting ſpirit hath and will bring perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuters to, that will not return at the Lords reproof.</p>
            <p>But they that have been armed with the Armour of Light and love, they through the faith, and power, and patience thereof overcome the envious perſecuting ſpirit in themſelvs firſt; and they are the called, and choſen, and faithful ones, that are with the Lamb, who have been exerciſed in the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare within, againſt the Devil, and all the fleſhly luſts, that have warred againſt the ſoul, firſt, before they came forth into the field, to joyn with Chriſt their Captain againſt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, or elſe the enemy within would make them turn to the enemy without, and ſo they in the faith and patience follow the Lamb, that taketh away the ſin in the regeneration within, before they come to joyn with him in open proclaimed wars againſt the Dragon and old Serpent, and <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> and all others that riſe up againſt the holy Seed Chriſt the Lamb, who is the leader of all the whole Camp of God, and the Captain of their ſalvation.</p>
            <p>And now all you great and ſmal, high and low people, even from the Kings and Princes to the middle ſort, and from them
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57002:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> to the meaneſt or leaſt degree of all, to whom this Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth happen, you have a deſcription of your greateſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, the ſpirit of envy and perſecution, which you are all required (and that by Special Warrant from your God that made you) to agree together, and ſtand up with one conſent, and with all your ſtrength of love, joyn your ſelves to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Principle of God in every particular, in order to the find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, ſtopping, apprehending, and taking of this inſufferable enemy to mans peace on earth, and good will towards one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, that Chriſt the Prince of peace may be chief among you all, to bring your ſouls into everlaſting peace with the father, in his everlaſting Kingdom.</p>
            <p>For of a truth, the Lord of Hoſts and his Son is ariſing in power and great glory from on High, to deſtroy the groſſe darkneſſe, and great City <hi>Babylon</hi> and Confuſion, which hath reigned over the Kings of the earth, and ſet them one againſt another to deſtroy one another: And this Author of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ſtrife, which is the ſpirit of pride and perſecution hath no place in Heaven, but is caſt out, and thrown down to the earth, and hath been, and ſtill is in a great rage, becauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>he hath but a ſhort time to reign there, and woe hath been, and ſtill is to the inhabitants of the earth,</hi> as it is ſaid in the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> And the Devil upon earth, and in the hearts of the children of diſobedience hath ſtirred many Kings one againſt another, and Nations, and all hath through ignorance roſe up againſt the Light and Lamb of God, but all they have and may do, and <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> together may riſe up, and joyn in battel againſt the Lamb, and his choſen ones the Saints of the Moſt High, yet as it is ſaid, <hi>The Lamb ſhall overcome them, for he is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, Rev. 17. 14. And they that are with him that over comes, are called, and choſen, and faithful; and when Gog and Magog, and their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, hath made themſelves in number as the ſand of the Sea, and hath ſpread themſelves on the bredth of the earth, and compaſſed the Camp of the Saints about, and the Beloved City; then ſhall fire come down from God out of Heaven, and devour them, and the Devil that deceived them, ſhall be caſt into the Lake, where the</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57002:13"/> 
               <hi>Fire never goeth out,</hi> as it is in <hi>Revelations</hi> the 20. He that hath an ear to hear, let him hear; and the meek ſhall eat, and he ſatisfied, they ſhall praiſe the Lord that ſeek him, your hearts ſhall live for ever, that draw neer unto him. Oh let all the ends of the world remember, and turn unto the Lord, and all the kindreds and Nations ſhall worſhip before thee, that obey thy voyce, and their peace ſhall be as a flood, and their righteouſneſſe as the waves of the Sea, and they that through faith and patience, and by the power of the word of God do overcome, they ſhall inherit all things in the Kingdome of God and his Chriſt, and they ſhall ſit down at the right hand of the Son of everlaſting life and glory, <hi>even as he overcame, and is ſate downe at the right hand of God, where is joy and pleaſure for evermore, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57002:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
